Stop!
止步
My friend left something up there.
我家老黄落了东西在上边
I'll only take that thing
我只取一样
and won't touch anything else.
其余不碰
Do we have to fight you?
那就是只能动手了呗
We're going to have a fight.
要跟这几位打架
What's your plan?
你咋办
I'll fight with you.
我与大哥一起冲杀
Good.
好
What a good brother.
真是好兄弟
You want to reap the spoils?
想等打起来捡漏是吧
What did you say?
大哥你说什么
I said I agreed with you.
我说我答应你
Since you decide to fight with me,
既然你要为大哥冲阵
I must help you out.
自然要成全我兄弟这一腔血勇
I'm just a child.
我还是个孩子
Get ready to fight my brother.
且看我家兄弟冲杀
Brother, you're highly skilled.
贤弟好武艺
Were you waiting for this moment?
你就等着这一下
I was waiting for you to crush our opponents.
可不就等着贤弟大杀四方吗
In fact, I don't work for Xu Fengnian.
其实我并非徐凤年手下
He told the truth.
说得对
Please go easy on him.
诸位手下留情啊
Hey, Brother.
大哥
Where did the boy come from?
这少年又是哪儿来的
After all, Xu is the son of Lord of North Liang.
毕竟是北椋世子
He's probably
想必
a secret guard of his.
是暗藏的护卫
The secret was kept well, then.
真是藏得够深的
It's never been exposed until now.
直到此刻才用出来
What an adept!
真是好身手
He must be Xu Fengnian's master card.
这大概就是徐凤年的杀招了
We've checked out
他身边那些人的路子
all the people around him
都算摸清了
except for the boy.
只有这个少年是个意外
We should spare no effort
等下出手
to kill him first.
全力杀他
Shouldn't we kill Xu Fengnian first?
不该先杀徐凤年吗
It's best if we can do that.
能先杀徐凤年自然最好
But look at him.
可是你看此人
Facing six martial slaves,
面对六名武奴
he still takes the lead.
依旧首当其冲
He's extremely loyal and brave.
忠勇之极
If we kill Xu Fengnian first,
要杀徐凤年
he'll surely step forward.
此人定会挺身而出
Let's be patient.
再等等
Sounds fair.
有道理
Stop!
站住
Your Highness,
世子
I think the martial slaves
感觉这些武奴
haven't tried their best to stop us.
并未尽全力拦我们
We've come this far.
都到这儿了
There's no need to turn round.
没必要回头
Here is a chance.
机会来了
Go.
上
There are 12 martial slaves in total.
一共十二位武奴
Yes.
没错
They're all here.
都在这了
You're here, too.
你也在
Your Highness, how are you?
世子你好
I'm your brother-in-law.
我是你姐夫
Hello, again.
又见面了
We are family.
自家亲戚
Let me help you.
我帮你吧
Are you suspicious of me?
连我都防着
I know Fujiang Armor.
伏将红甲我认得
What if I say it has nothing to do with me?
我要说伏将红甲跟我没关系呢
Do you think I'll believe it?
你觉得我信吗
I won't join you, then.
我不参战
Enjoy your fight.
诸位随意
Your Highness, please.
世子
You want to kick me when I'm down?
这是要当黄雀
Facing the six martial slaves,
那六位出手
I don't think you'll be well protected.
你身边的怕是护不周全
What if I go no further
我要是不再前进
and leave for good?
就此离开呢
Your Highness, you're not that kind of person.
世子您不是这样的人
You're right.
也对
Your Highness,
世子
we're attacked from front and rear.
前后夹击
The situation goes against us.
时局不利
When soldiers are besieged by the enemy
用兵者被敌围困
and can't find a way out,
难寻出路
what should they do?
该如何
They should fight their way out.
那就杀出条路来
Yes.
对
Fight our way out.
杀出条路来
Iron Armor.
玄甲
Green Plum.
青梅
Bamboo Horse.
竹马
Spring Water.
春水
Morning Dew.
朝露
Peach Blossom.
桃花
Rise.
起
Go.
去
Why do you stop?
怎么不打了
Deng Tai'e joined in.
那一位既然出手
It makes no difference
拦不拦的
whether they fight or not.
也就没意义了
Come back.
回来
Thanks for the sword.
多谢前辈一剑之恩
Thanks for the six swords.
多谢前辈六剑之恩
Senior, if I may ask,
敢问前辈
are you Sword God Peach Blossom?
可是桃花剑神
I am Deng Tai'e.
我是邓太阿
I remember
这份恩情
your kindness.
徐凤年记着
I'll return the favor in the future.
将来再报
You have nothing to return.
不是你报
I was returning you a favor.
是我报恩
Xu Fengnian.
徐凤年
Your mother
你娘
was a distant cousin to me.
是我远房的表姐
Was that some kind of kinship?
这也能攀上亲戚
How lucky he is
胎投得
born in such a family.
是真好
When I was practicing swordplay in Sword Tomb of the Wu family,
当年我在吴家剑冢练剑之时
your mother did me many favors
你娘对我
of giving me meals,
有一饭之恩
saving my life,
有救命之恩
and
有
giving me instruction.
授业之恩
Those were great favors.
这恩情太大
How could I not return?
怎能不还
Sadly,
只可惜
when you mother went to the imperial city alone,
你娘当年孤身入皇城时
I was outside the East Sea.
我人在东海之外
When I came back,
待我归来
it was too late.
一切都晚了
She got hurt in fighting
你娘那一战
and was never cured.
落下病根
At last, she died.
最终殒命
Every time I think about it,
回想起来
I feel guilty.
我愧疚至今
The favors I owed to your mother,
我欠你娘的恩情
today, I've returned a half
今日这六剑
using the six swords.
算是还了一半
On the wall,
城头之上
you can take
你想拿些什么
whatever you want to.
安心拿便是
The 12 flying swords
这十二柄飞剑
have been with me throughout my life.
也算是追随邓某一生
Today,
今日
I give them to you.
赠于世子
The art of killing with flying swords
这飞剑杀人之术
lies in the box.
全在此匣之中
It's up to you whether you can
能不能够领悟得到
comprehend it or not.
就全靠世子你自己了
I've returned the other half
这剩下的一半恩情
of the favors.
至此报完
Your Highness.
世子
From now on,
从此你我
we don't owe each other again.
互不相欠
Thanks.
多谢
Your Highness, put the flying swords away first.
世子先把飞剑收了吧
Later.
回头收
The flying sword skill of Sword God Peach Blossom
桃花剑神的飞剑术
is supreme and unique.
武林里的无上绝学啊
I know.
我知道
But I'm shortsighted.
谁让我眼光浅呢
Right now,
这时候
the sword box is the most important thing to me.
那个剑匣才是天才第一重要
Mr. Deng,
邓先生
if you want to kill me,
您若是要给我一剑
you'd better do it early,
不如早点动手
lest I'm agitated
我在这边上等着
waiting here.
心里不是事儿
I've returned all the favors
恩情还尽
and finished what has started.
因果皆了
He has nothing to do with me now.
世子与我无关了
So,
那
if I'm going to strike Xu Fengnian,
我若是等会儿对徐凤年出手
won't you use your swords?
您不出剑
My swords
我的剑
were given away.
已经送人了
As Sword God Peach Blossom,
邓先生这般身份
your every word must carry weight.
定是一言九鼎
Not now.
这会儿不打
I'm not stupid.
我也不傻
The first half of the favors Mr. Deng has to return
人家邓先生前一半恩情
is to help your master
就是助你家世子
take the sword box on the wall.
去城头取剑匣
If I'm going to strike him,
我要出手
I would wait until he gets the box
也得等他拿完东西
and Mr. Deng finishes returning the favor.
人家恩情还完了再说
Now, no one in the world
这会儿天底下
could stop your master
没人阻得了你家世子
from getting the box.
取剑匣
Is this yours?
这是你的
His Highness's talking to you.
世子问你话呢
Answer the question.
你赶紧回啊
It's mine.
是我的
Your Highness,
世子
he is the new groom.
这是府上新来的马夫
He doesn't need to
带来的旧东西
take the old stuff into the mansion.
就不带进府里了
Yeah.
嗯
How long have you been taking it?
这东西你带着多久了
Very long.
带着很久了
It's your stuff.
这是你的就是你的
Take it.
拿着
I don't necessarily need it.
可以不要了
My mother used to say,
我娘说了
what accompanied you
陪着你的是缘分
had a bond with you,
也是情分
no matter it's a person or a thing.
人和物都是如此
I don't quite understand it.
其实我也不太懂这句话
Anyway, don't throw your old stuff away.
反正别乱扔旧东西
When you want it back in the future,
将来想要了
how can you find it?
哪儿找呀
Guess what I've found?
你猜我找着什么了
Ah?
啊
What did you find?
找着什么
Look.
你看
I got it back for you.
我给你找回来了
I don't necessarily need it.
也可以不要了
All these years,
这么多年了
you've been taking it with you.
你一直带着它
It must be important to you.
它对你很重要
It's all in the past.
那都是过去的事了
Why deny the man who you used to be?
干嘛否定过去的自己啊
Don't you think he made the man
没有曾经的你
who you are today?
哪有现在的你啊
Anyway,
不管怎么样
you're Old Huang to me.
对我来说你就是老黄
Since it was the will of heaven
既然天意
that helped you find it...
让你把它给找出来了
Don't throw it again.
那你别再扔了
What's your surname?
你姓什么
It's Huang.
我姓黄
I'll call you Old Huang, then.
那我就叫你老黄吧
OK.
好啊
♪Old dog Old dog♪
老狗老狗
♪There is no dog like you♪
天下没有
♪Tail broken♪
断了尾巴
♪There is♪
没了
♪No way back♪
归路
♪Old dog Old dog♪
老狗老狗
♪There is no dog like you♪
天下没有
♪Buried in the earth♪
土里埋骨
♪Distress in the joy♪
甜里寻苦
Common people use fire,
世人以炉火炼剑
copper and iron,
以金铁炼剑
as well as spirit lifeblood to forge swords.
以气血炼剑
Today,
今日
by force of yin and yang,
我借阴阳之机
flame of heart light,
心光之焱
power of thunderbolt,
借雷霆淬砺
unity of heaven and earth,
乾坤作冶
till now,
直至今日
I finally perfected
终于
the sword intent.
剑成
Open
一剑
the Heaven's Gate.
开天门
Li Chungang is a real sword god.
好一个剑神李淳罡
Excellent.
好剑
My sword intent
李淳罡此剑
could open the Heaven's Gate.
开得天门
Could it kill you?
杀得你王仙芝否
What a great
好一个
sword intent!
一剑开天门
Junior Master,
小师叔
did you steal vegetables again?
又去偷菜了
What's wrong?
这是怎么了
I have no idea.
不知道啊
He was just fine.
小师叔刚才好好的
What happened to him?
怎么成这样了
Junior Master.
小师叔
- Don't touch him. - Junior Master.
别动他
What happened?
怎么回事
Junior Master stood here still just now,
小师叔方才呆立在这儿
gazing at the skyline.
望着天边
Suddenly he became like this.
突然就成这样了
Which direction?
哪个方向
- There.
那边
The east.
是东方啊
Put up a shed over his head.
就地给他搭个棚子
And then?
然后呢
Don't do anything else.
然后什么都不需要做
Wait till he wakes up.
等他自己醒来
What happened in the east
东方发生了什么
that woke you up?
能敲醒了你
The moment finally comes.
终于等到这一刻
I've never seen such a fight.
就没见过这么打架的
What an eye-opener!
真是开眼界了
Do you think
你说
they are still human?
他们还是人吗
Yes.
是
I don't know about Wang Xianzhi.
王仙芝我不清楚
But Sword God Li is definitely human.
李剑神绝对还是人
Have you got the sword box?
剑匣取回来了
Can I fight you now?
那我可以继续动手了吗
Do you think you have any chance?
你觉得你还有机会吗
Sword God Li is busy now.
李剑神刚出剑
Do you think he can take care of you?
你觉得他还顾得上你吗
There is another one hiding in here?
还有个人藏在这里
Sword God Peach Blossom
桃花剑神在此
didn't just come for Xu Fengnian, did you?
不仅仅是为徐凤年吧
Nice to meet you, Master Zhao.
见过赵老天师
Do you know me?
你认得我
Though I've never met you,
虽未谋面
your name
却也听闻过
pierced my ear like thunder.
赵老天师的风采
What a coincidence.
也是难得
Of the few people who know me,
知道我的人极少
I actually come across one.
怎么就遇上一个
You're lucky.
你运气不错
I don't understand.
没明白
After Li Chungang and Wang Xianzhi started to fight,
李淳罡和王仙芝动手之后
I was planning to kill you,
我就能杀你了
but in my heart lake,
可偏偏心湖内
I perceived a peerless master
感受到武帝城外
outside Wudi City.
有绝世高手
I then decided to wait,
便想着再等等
not expecting it was Sword God Peach Blossom
没想到等了个
who came to pay a debt of gratitude.
桃花剑神的报恩局
When you fought the martial slaves just now,
方才阁下与武奴动手时
did you hide your capacities?
藏了手段
I was messing with them.
闹着玩玩
Why should I be serious?
何必较真呢
What's your real identity?
敢问阁下的身份是
There is no need to hide it now.
被认出来就不瞒了
I'm from Mount Longhu,
贫道龙虎山
Zhao Xuansu.
赵宣素
The generation of Xuan?
宣字辈
Your Highness,
世子
the generation of Xuan is two generations senior
宣字辈可比当今的龙虎掌门
than the Master of Mount Longhu.
还高了两辈
I'm afraid Master Zhao
眼前这位
is almost 140 years old.
怕是已经活了两个古稀
I've guessed you might attack me,
猜到阁下要对我动手
not expecting you are of such a high generation.
但没想到辈分这么高
It must be hard for you
也是难为赵老神仙了
to call me Brother these days.
这几日还要管我叫大哥
I don't care about it.
我都不在乎
Why should you care?
你在乎什么
May I venture to ask if you still want to kill me?
敢问阁下还杀我吗
I was planning to do so.
本来还是该杀一杀
But Deng Tai'e is here, after all.
毕竟邓太阿在
I should show some respect to him.
该留几分面子
Senior,
前辈
you come to kill Xu Fengnian, too?
也是来杀徐凤年的
Senior Deng just said,
方才邓前辈说过
he had finished returning favors.
他的恩情已经报完了
From now on,
之后
Xu Fengnian's life or death has nothing to do with him.
徐凤年的生死均与他无关
This Young Master
眼前这位世子
deserves to be killed.
还是可以杀一杀的
I'd like to join hands with you.
晚辈愿与前辈联手
If Senior Deng doesn't help,
如果桃花剑神不出手
these people
眼前这些人
can't stop you.
是拦不住前辈的
The Fujiang Armor below is yours?
下面的伏将红甲是你的
If you like,
若前辈喜欢
just take it.
可拿去赏玩
Are you Zhao Kai?
你就是赵楷
You know me?
前辈知道我
I won't kill Xu Fengnian.
徐凤年我不杀了
It makes
杀你
no difference to kill you.
也一样
Do you try to resist me with a puppet?
一具傀儡也想破局
If I said or did anything wrong,
晚辈要是说错话做错事
I apologize for it.
愿向前辈谢罪
Xu Fengnian is the cause of chaos,
徐凤年是大乱之因
so are you.
你也一样
Mount Longhu is in debt to His Majesty.
龙虎山既受皇恩
Let me kill you today
今日就取你性命
to return the favor.
还份恩情吧
Are you crazy?
这是疯了
Why do you save him?
你救他
Senior Zhao, please go easy on him.
赵老神仙手下留情
He was trying to kill you all the way.
他一路都在杀你
Can you tell me
能不能说一下
why you want to
救我这事
save me?
你怎么想的
You shouldn't
你的绝路
die here.
不该在这儿
Why don't you run?
还不走
Thinking about it over and over again,
想来想去
I still don't know the reason why you saved him.
也想不出你救他的理由
Normally,
按常理来说
you might be crazy.
你应该是疯了
I might be.
有可能
But I know,
可我知道
you're deep-minded.
你小子心思极深
The reason
你救他
why you saved him
必定是
must be extremely important.
有一个极其重要的原因在
I apologize.
给赵老神仙赔罪
Young people
现在的年轻人
are more and more surprising now.
真是越来越了不得
If Deng Tai'e isn't here,
要不是邓太阿在
I might have killed you.
我真该杀了你
Please show mercy
还请赵老神仙手下留情
and let those two go.
放过那二位
Anyway, you'll get what you deserve in the future.
反正将来都是你自己的劫数
What was happening?
这都什么局面
Thank you very much.
多谢老神仙
You didn't come here
老神仙这次来武帝城
just to kill us, did you?
不仅仅是为了杀人吧
I'll take the chance to ascend to heaven
自然是为了开天门
when Heaven's Gate opens.
求飞升
Heaven's Gate?
天门
When you come to the ultimate realm of martial arts,
武学到了极致
you may have the chance to become an immortal.
就有飞升为仙的机会
To do that,
要飞升
you must wait till Heaven's Gate opens.
就要打开天门
Though I look like a boy,
我虽身如少年
I'm getting rotten inwardly.
内在却接近腐坏
After all, I've been waiting for 120 years.
毕竟等了两个甲子
Why did you tell me this?
老神仙连这都告诉我了
I finally get the chance ascending to heaven.
终于有了登仙之机
It doesn't hurt to tell you.
这些话说说也无所谓了
Heaven's Gate reopens
天门重开
because of the fight between Sword God Li and Wang Xianzhi?
是因为李剑神与王仙芝一战
I'm afraid the gate only reopens
怕也只有这两个人交手
because of their fight.
天门才会重开
I'm not wrong.
我没来错
The gate is opening.
天门将开
The wonderland will befall.
仙界重临
I can finally take the step.
我终于能迈出这一步
Sword God Peach Blossom
桃花剑神
came here
此来武帝城
for this, too, I suppose.
想必也是为了此事
You're right.
你还说对了
I do come for Heaven's Gate.
我还真是为了天门而来
The gate is about to open.
天门眼看就要打开
We both have the chance to ascend.
你我都有飞升机会
Maybe we can work together.
或许还能合作行事
They're fighting with all their strength.
这二人全力交锋了
It's only one step away.
只差一步了
Shall we continue?
还打吗
Heaven's Gate is opening.
天门将开
The outcome is still pending.
胜负未决
What are they doing?
李淳罡和王仙芝在做什么
Why do they stop?
怎么停手了
For decades,
数十年来
this is the only chance to open Heaven's Gate.
唯一一次开天门的机会
Are they going to let it go?
他们俩就准备放过了不成
Maybe they don't want to
或许他们二位
ascend to heaven.
不愿飞升呢
They don't want to?
不愿飞升
Why not?
为何不愿
They perhaps would rather stay on earth
或许比起仙界
than go to the wonderland.
他们更想留在人间
What on earth deserves to stay for?
人间有什么可留的
How can they miss the chance?
这种机会怎能错过
The moment has already come.
如今契机已成
With extra force,
再加一份力
we can open Heaven's Gate
便能打开天门
and welcome the wonderland.
迎回仙界
In this case,
既然如此
let me open the gate.
就由我来打开天门吧
Rise.
剑起
Deng Tai'e, what are you doing?
邓太阿你做什么
You just said something wrong.
老天师方才有句话说错了
I do come here
邓某此来武帝城
for Heaven's Gate.
确实是为了仙界天门
However,
只不过
I don't want it to open.
不是等它打开
What do you want, then?
那你要的是什么
I want to
我要的是
stop it from opening
阻拦天门重开
and cut off the connection
要仙界
between the wonderland and the earth.
与人间断了往来
Why?
为什么
Ancient books
历来古籍
have recorded
素有记录
the visits of immortals.
仙人下界
The so-called immortals
所谓仙人
have long cast their mortal hearts away.
早已抛却人心
They think they represent heaven's way.
以天道自处
Every time when immortals befall,
每逢仙人临凡
they would change
仅凭喜好
the world's situation at will.
便要改换天下之势
Diversion of rivers
江河改流
and shift of mountains
山川移位
usually happen.
都属平常
What's more,
更有甚者
some immortals would decide human's life or death
仅凭一己之好恶
according to their likes and dislikes.
便要断人间之生死
Numerous people die
不知换来
because of them.
多少白骨累累
So what?
那又怎样
The change of dynasties in the world
世上王朝更迭
also causes numerous death.
不也是杀戮不断
If nothing else,
别的不说
he is the son of Lord of North Liang.
这位是北椋世子
How many people died because of his father?
他爹徐骁当年杀了多少人
Why don't you kill him?
怎不见你提剑斩杀
The change of dynasties
王朝更迭
is the struggle of human.
乃是人间自己之争斗
I've never wanted to
我从未想过
stop all the killings in the world.
让天下无杀戮
As a matter of fact,
说起来
the swordplay I've been practicing
我自己所练的
is the art of killing.
就是杀人之剑
But human's affairs
可是人间之事
should be decided by human.
自然由人来决定
The mortal world
这人间
doesn't need immortals.
不需要仙人
Just because of that,
就为这个
you want to stop Heaven's Gate from reopening,
你要拦下天门重开
and block the way of all martial artists in the world?
断了天下武学者的前进之路吗
I am
邓某
never a reasonable man.
从来就不是讲道理的人
Stopping me from ascending,
你拦我飞升之路
you're my sworn enemy.
你我便是不共戴天之敌
You can't stop me, anyway!
你也拦不住我
Emei, Rosefinch,
峨眉 朱雀
Phoenix Tree, Ant,
黄桐 蚍蜉
Golden Thread, Tai'e,
金缕 太阿
rise.
起
Swords array.
剑阵
The swords array is called Disarm.
此剑阵取名兵解
It was originally prepared for Wang Xianzhi.
本来是为王仙芝而准备
I didn't expect
却不想
I would use it against you.
用到了阁下身上
I'd like to see
我倒要看看
if you can really disarm me.
邓剑神能否兵解贫道
Go.
去
Power of stars,
星辰之力
might of thunder?
雷池之威
Deng Tai'e,
邓太阿
how dare you?
你怎敢如此
Go.
去
Deng Tai'e,
邓太阿
you stand in my way of ascending.
你阻我飞升之路
I must kill all your relatives and friends.
我必要杀尽你血脉亲朋
Master Zhao,
赵老天师
stop now,
此时收手
and your life can be saved.
还能保住性命
Why bother like this?
你这又何苦呢
Doing that,
如此作为
you'll kill yourself.
岂不是断了自己的生路
Being in Unity Realm,
天人之境
how can I be confined?
岂受他人束缚
I'm sick
这人间
of the world!
我已待腻了
Born human,
生而为人
but you're sick of the world.
却腻了人间
How pathetic you are!
何其可笑
Since we've achieved to Unity Realm,
我等既入天人之境
we're no longer an ordinary person.
便再也不算普通凡人
In order to get stronger,
只是为了变强
are you really going
真的要抛弃那颗
to cast away your mortal heart?
做人的心吗
What if I do?
我扔了又如何
Senior Zhao,
赵老天师
I won't allow
邓某的剑下
any immortals to be in the world.
不许人间有仙
Xu Fengnian!
徐凤年
Since he is your benefactor's son,
他既然与你有恩
I'll kill him in front of you.
我就让他死在你面前
Don't dream of ascending to heaven!
老子让你登仙
The Ninth Move,
剑九
Six Thousand Li!
六千里
Back off!
快退